This episode is about the internet celebrities taking the postgraduate entrance exam
这一期讲一讲网红考研
And also about the homestead issue
讲一讲宅基地的事啊
Because a friend of mine has been urging me
因为我的一个朋友一直在催我
Talk about both the postgraduate exam and the homestead issue
跟这个关于考研的跟宅基地的事
He really wants to see my discussion on this topic.
他特别想看我关于这方面的论述
Because it's been quite popular lately.
因为这方面最近在说的比较火啊
But I spent a lot of time researching it.
但是呢我查了半天资料啊
I spent a lot of time researching it.
我查了半天资料
And I even asked Deep Sick for some advice.
然后包括在问deep sick
To give me some suggestions and so on.
让他给我点建议什么之类的
I found their advice was too positive.
我发现他们的建议都太正面了
Their advice was too positive.
他们的建议都太正面了
It's not the more negative perspective I was looking for.
不并不是我想说的那个比较负面的感觉
Hehe, so as a commentary
呵呵所以作为commentary
Given the nature of my show
作为我这节目的尿性来讲呢
I won’t strictly follow the deep sick arrangement
我还是会不是按照deep sick给我去安排的
in that direction
这种方向去说哇
I’ll share my own feelings
我会说我自己的感觉啊
First, let me mention one thing
首先我先说一个啊
I watched a video by Professor Zheng Qiang before.
就是我之前看了郑强教授的一个视频
I still really like Professor Zheng Qiang
然后郑强教授这个人我还是很喜欢他的
But regarding his recent comments I strongly disagree with that. He has a video where he says this that young Chinese people are particularly arrogant, calling Japan 'Little Japan', and South Korea 'Little Korea',
但是关于他这番言论 我特别的不以为然 他有一个视频是这么说的 说这个中国人这个年轻人特别狂啊 管日本叫小日子 管这个这个韩国叫小棒子
and Indians 'A-San',
管这个印度人叫阿三啊
and looking down on Black people.
还看不起黑人
And every year,
然后这个这个这个这个每年
so many Japanese win Nobel Prizes.
日本得诺贝尔奖的人那么多
Look, how many does China have?
你看中国才几个
Many places in China are not even as good as Japan.
中国很多地方还不如人家日本
And the QS ranking, the university ranking isn't high either.
然后这个QS排名也是学校排名不靠前
I mean,
我就说啊
Professor Zheng Qiang,
郑强教授
I've always respected him,
我一向很尊重他
but I didn't expect him to make such a damn stupid statement.
但是我没想到他能发出这么他妈弱智的言论啊
First, what's wrong with calling them 'Little Japs'?
首先叫小日子怎么了
Then, what's wrong with calling them 'Little Bastards'?
那我叫小棒子怎么了
What's wrong with calling them A San?
我叫他们阿三就怎么了
They're so dirty
脏成那个样
Can't let people say that, can we?
不能让人说是吗
Their self-esteem is bigger than their behinds
自尊心呢看的比屁股都大
Can't let them say that, can we?
不能说是吗
What's wrong with talking about the good life?
再说说小日子怎么了
Right?
是不是
Is it normal for me to talk about the big life?
难道我说大日子很正常嘛
It's not about discrimination; it's something that comes with this kind of teasing
不是歧视和这种调侃都会有的东西
Is that right?
对不对
So, am I being discriminatory towards Black people in China? Do you professors hope to bring these people in? To come to China for university? Then our students have six to a room,
那我有没有歧视在中国的黑人 你们这些教授希望引进这些人啊 来到中国读大学 然后呢自己的学生六人间
While foreign students have two to a room,
然后外国的学生二人间
And they have electricity 24/7,
然后24小时不断电
Do you think what you said is correct?
你觉得你说的很对吗
Let's be honest
而且咱们说实在的
What if the Nobel Prize doesn't go to a Chinese person?
诺贝尔奖不发给中国人又怎么了
First, we should mention that perhaps the most anti-China country in Europe
首先我们说全世界可能最反华的一个欧洲国家
is Sweden
就是他们瑞典
Remember that travel show they produced?
记着瑞典制作的那个关于旅游节目
It was specifically insulting to Chinese people
专门侮辱中国人
and they never apologized for it
什么事后也不道歉啊
Look at Sweden
你看瑞典
Look at how P-She does it, right?
你看这P社对不对
The recently released map has some issues.
最近出的这个有问题的地图
Sweden has long been a country with a particular prejudice against Chinese people.
瑞典一直是一个老牌的特别歧视华人的国家
He has become somewhat pathological.
他已经有点病态了
Why would he be willing to award your scientists?
他他怎么会愿意给你的科学家去发奖呢
Occasionally, when there's no other choice,
偶尔实在不行了
he gives out an award.
他发一个奖
He awards those writers,
发那些文学家
those thinkers, and the like.
那些讲那些思想家之类的
So-called and so forth.
所谓的那些之类
He's looking at you too
他也是看你啊
If you're anti-China
如果你反华
So they're giving you this award as well, right
所以呢也给你这个奖对吧
We're not saying that everyone he talks about has issues
咱们也不是说所有的这些他给讲的人都有问题
But is this an issue The enemy of my enemy is my friend And the QS rankings Are put together by a British consulting firm A British consulting firm would naturally favor the new British universities Is that right?
但是这是不是一个问题 就是敌人的敌人就是自己的朋友 再加上QS排名那种东西 是英国的一个咨询公司搞出来的 英国咨询搞出来肯定就是每家新英 对不对
Japan, as their little ally
日本又作为他们的小盟国
their small ally
小盟友
is it the most, you know, Westernized country in Asia
是不是亚洲最那什么的
the most Western country
最最白人的国家
That’s just how he puts it
这不是他就是这么说
talking about leaving Asia and joining Europe
脱亚入欧嘛
Isn't that so?
对不对
Aren't you going to do Yu Ji's theory?
不做于吉的理论吗
So, your thing, Japan has always been America's lapdog, right?
所以你这东西呢日本他一直就是美国的小狗嘛
It's a protectorate, isn't it?
就是一个保护国嘛对吧
Fifty-five, fifty-one states, right?
五十五五十一个州嘛
So, how do you put it?
所以你怎么说这东西的
Sweden would definitely give America some face, wouldn't it?
瑞典也肯定得给美国面子
Right?
对不对
Of course, there are no Japanese who would give Japan face.
当然给日本面子没日本人
Scientists, one every year, one each year.
科学家每年一个每年一个
What kind of level are you, Zheng Qiang?
你郑强什么样水平的人
Your statement is so impressive.
你这个言论那么的牛逼
Why are you defending them now?
你现在为什么要替人家说话
I just don't understand.
我就不明白了
You don't win the Nobel Prize.
你们不拿诺贝尔
You don't win the Nobel Prize, then what?
不拿诺贝尔吧
The QS ranking doesn't go up, so what?
QS排名上不去上不去呗
Why do you keep talking about winning or not winning the Nobel Prize?
为什么你要拿拿不拿诺贝尔奖
As a criterion to judge whether our scientists are outstanding or not?
作为评判我们的科学家厉害不厉害的标准呢
Scientists are impressive.
那科学家厉害
They just need to produce research results.
他出科研成果就完了呗
Why does he have to publish in international journals? Isn't that just your obsession? Right? You think winning a Nobel Prize Publishing in international journals And then attracting foreign students Makes something truly impressive.
他干嘛非得上国际期刊 这不就是你们的有病吗 对不对 你们认为拿了诺奖 上了国际期刊 然后引进了外国留学生 这个东西就叫这个东西有有有厉害
This thing demonstrates a high level of scientific research.
这个东西它就有科研水平
Is your criteria for evaluation flawed?
你这是是你的评判标准有问题吗
It's the mindset of your generation, the one obsessed with the literature of trauma, that's the issue.
是你们伤痕文学这一代的思想有问题吧
Right?
对不对
We young people don't want to carry that burden.
我们年轻人可不背这包袱啊
Let's be honest.
咱们说实在
Of course, I belong to a younger generation than they do.
当然我比他们要年轻一代啊
More than just one generation.
不止一代了
Now, let's get back to discussing the postgraduate entrance exam.
然后咱们继续说这考研的问题啊
Zhang Jingchu is preparing for the postgraduate entrance exam.
张静初考研
Then there's that Velociraptor who's also preparing for the exam.
然后那个那个那个什么迅猛龙考研
And many others, I can't quite remember.
然后很多人什么还有什么呃
What was their name again?
叫叫什么来着
That internet celebrity.
那个网红啊
She memorized 500 IELTS words in just two hours.
这个两两个小时背了500个雅思单词啊
Firstly, I want to say that the internet celebrity preparing for the exam has their own reasons.
首先我要说网红考研他有自己的考虑的地方啊
I've always been against recommending people to pursue a master’s degree.
我一向是不推荐人考研啊
So I'm not keen on talking about anything that promotes postgraduate studies.
所以我就不愿意去说利于考研的东西
When it comes to the postgraduate entrance exam,
因为考研这个东西呢
the success rate is very low each year,
每年的这个成功率呢非常的低
and it's been declining year by year.
而且是逐年下降呃
Many people take the exam primarily because they want to stay at their alma mater,
很多人考研的主要原因是因为啊想留校
or because the exam serves as a way to defer employment. or because they want to take the exam themselves, with the hope of becoming a civil servant in the future. I understand all of these reasons, but you need to be aware that the acceptance rate has been decreasing year after year.
或者说是因为考研是延迟就业的一种方式 或者说因为自己考研 将来想考公务员之类的 这我都理解 但是你一定要知道他的录取率是连年下降的
You shouldn’t get caught up in the competition.
你不能去卷的
The more you do, the more intense it gets.
越卷越厉害
That’s just how it is.
就这样
I don't recommend pursuing a master's degree first.
我首先不推荐考研
A second master’s degree.
二考研
You’re spending time on things like an MBA.
你花那个时间去读什么MBA之类的那种东西
Firstly, you’re spending money on an MBA.
首先花钱读MBA
You could do so much with that money.
那钱你都可以干很多事情了
Secondly, an MBA won’t help you start a business.
二读NBA对你创造一个企业没有用
It's just for working in large corporations.
他只是给你在大企业中打工用的
And it's not really that practical.
而且那个东西其实不是特别的不是特别的实用
A lot of things aren't practical.
很多东西都不实用
Jingchu Zhang
张静初
He took this test
他考这东西
He already has money and fame.
他是他已经有钱有名声了
Like many of these internet celebrities
像很多的这些网红
They took the exam when they already had money and fame.
他们考研有钱有名声了
He's doing well streaming his postgraduate exam preparation process.
他去直播自己考研的过程不错
But let me tell you
但是我跟你讲
the exams are over
考完了
you have to study for three years for a Master's degree
你学硕你要年3年啊
and two years for a professional Master's
专硕要念两年
this thing
这个东西
the time commitment isn't something everyone can manage
这个时间耗费起来不是任何人都能行的
like someone my age
比如说我这种岁数的人
I'm just right for taking the postgraduate entrance exam
我就适合考研啊
so what happened after I took the exam
我考了以后怎么样了
After passing the exam, I can teach at a larger institution.
考了以后再大的机构当老师
But how long can I teach, really? I'm taking the exam this year. I graduated at 44. Then I started teaching at a university. And I plan to teach for another 10 years. Then I'll retire. What's the point of that?
但我当老师我能当几年啊 我今年考啊 我44岁毕业 然后我去大学当老师 然后我再干个10年 我就退休了 那有什么必要呢
I can start now.
我现在就可以干
I'm now really passionate about teaching performance.
我现在如果特别热心于表演教学事业
I could go work at an art school right now.
我现在就可以去艺考机构干
I could also teach at a community college.
我现在可以去大专干
I might just not be able to stay on as a lecturer at an undergraduate institution.
我只不过可能不能留校本科再说留校本科
The students in this year's class,
人家本届的这一届的学生
they are working as teaching assistants.
人家呢在那当助教
as a TA,
当ta
and then end up,
然后落着
and eventually compete for a professorship.
最后咱在那去争那个教授那位置
I really think it's just so boring
我觉得真的是非常的没有意思
If you spend that time fighting for a graduate school spot
你有那个时间去争研究生那个位置
You could have made a fortune doing something else by now
你干别的早发财了啊
I've always encouraged young people to start their own careers early
我一直是鼓励年轻人早早的做自己的事业
Whether it's starting a business or doing trade
创业或者做生意
It doesn't necessarily have to be starting a business
不一定非要创业
It doesn't have to be working for a startup
不一定非要干初创公司
But you can be a sole proprietor
但是你可以干个体户啊
You can do trade
可以做生意
So I strongly advise against taking the postgraduate entrance exam.
所以我是坚决不推荐大家考研的
The cost-benefit ratio is just too low.
因为考研的性价比太低了啊
Let's talk about the homestead issue next.
第三件事咱们说一说这宅基地的问题
Some people say that if you don’t return to the homestead within five years,
有人说这宅基地如果那个5年之内不回去的话
it will be reclaimed.
这宅基地就会啊这个收走啊
And others mention that homesteads can’t be bought or sold. That’s just ridiculous. I totally understand the desire to live a pastoral life. But if homesteads were allowed to be bought and sold, you wouldn't get what you expect, you know,
然后有人说啊 宅基地不让买卖啊 那个太那什么了 我非常理解大家想过田园生活的心情 但是宅基地如果让买卖的话 你能得到的绝对不是你知道吗
they definitely wouldn't leave it for you,
一定不会留给你
it would certainly be taken over by large corporations or trusts,
一定会被大型的这些公司托拉斯给兼并
which would lead to all sorts of major issues,
就是引起那个什么什么的一大问题
so it's absolutely crucial not to let this happen,
所以千万不能就是谷地
it must be owned by the state,
一定是收归国家所有啊
there must be no room for individuals to trade them freely,
一定不能说个人随便买卖
but as a benefit for wealthy rural residents,
但是作为一个农村富豪的福利来讲的话
So, should we really be talking about it?
到底要不要拿着它来讲的话
Many people work between cities,
就很多人在城市之间工作
or they have already settled into their jobs in the city.
或者在城市的工作已经稳定了
So, they have given up on this.
所以这个东西他就已经放弃了
Therefore, these things gradually circulate.
所以这些东西逐渐的流转
Gradually, what happens is,
逐渐的什么
This is a very normal occurrence.
这是一个很正常的事情
There’s no need to overanalyze it.
不用去过度解读它
But I think for those of us who do self-media,
但是我认为如果像我我们这种做自媒体的人
If there's a plot of land in the rural hometown,
如果农村老家有一片宅基地的话
I would be willing to build a house there myself.
我是愿意把他自建一个房子的
Build a house myself,
自建一个房子
and make it feel like a standalone villa.
把它建成别墅的独栋别墅的感觉
To be honest,
说实在的
as long as you have electricity,
你只要通上电
internet access,
通上网
and water supply,
通上水
and all sorts of other amenities.
通上乱七八糟的东西
You could even build a garage yourself The cost of building a villa is actually around 1 million or 2 million If you're in the city you'd have to buy a even in Changsha a villa in Chengdu would cost two to three million
你自己又能弄车库 这个东西一个别墅造价其实来讲就是100万啊 200万左右啊 你要在城市中 你买一个 哪怕是长沙的 成都的别墅也得两三百万
and it might still be a townhouse
而且可能还是叠拼
or even a semi-detached one
有可能还是联排啊
Is that right?
对不对
Then it's not worth the money, is it?
那就不值那个钱啊
Villas in Beijing can easily cost over 9 million RMB.
北京的别墅动辄就900多万
Even in this trending area with over 19 million
甚至这热门地区1900多万
Do you think it’s worth the money?
你说这东西值那个钱吗
Houses in Houston, USA,
美国休斯敦的房子
a large standalone villa only costs about 2.7 million RMB.
大别墅独栋的也就270多万人民币
Is that right?
对不对
So there’s no need for you to buy this house.
所以你没有必要去买这个房子
And when it comes to homesteads, they are the most suitable option.
而且宅基地来讲是最合适的
If you want to live in a large mansion,
如果你想住大豪宅的话
I suggest that if any of you have a homestead
我建议就是说如果你们有宅基地的小朋友
don’t give it up under any circumstances.
一定不要放弃宅基地
It’s a significant benefit.
这是一个非常大的一个福利
Looking to the future,
因为未来来讲的话
in terms of real estate,
一定是房地产来讲的话
the enthusiasm in second, third, fourth, and fifth-tier cities will gradually wane,
在2345线城市逐渐的退去这个热潮
but first-tier cities will still maintain a growth trend.
一线城市它仍然会保持一个增长的一个态势
Because this is about the trend of the future
因为这就是未来的一个走势问题
So if you can build a big house at home
所以如果你能在自家建大房子来讲
It's still a good thing
仍然是一个好事
But not everyone is suited for returning to their hometown to start a business
但是不是所有人都适合回乡创业
If you're in the live e-commerce business
如果你是做直播电商
Or promoting a certain type of agricultural product Or processing a certain type of agricultural by-product You can return to your hometown You can go back to your hometown to do these things Encouraging villagers to develop together This is a good thing But if you're like me, an individual media creator
或者你做某一种农产品的推广 或者做某种农副加工品的东西 你可以回乡 你可以去回乡去做这些东西 带动村民一起发展 这是件好事 但如果你就像我这种个人的自媒体来讲
There are actually many benefits to returning to your hometown
其实回乡也有很多的好处
Many of the media creators you see
很多的你看那些自媒体之类的
We won't get into the Northeast dialect here
他都是以咱们就不说东北语节了
They all focus on rural themes
都是以这个呃农村为主题的
It's actually like this
其实这也这样了哇
It helps to attract more traffic
更好获得流量
This is a good thing.
这是件好事
But this decision must be based on individual circumstances.
但是这个东西一定要根据个人的条件来决定
Like whether or not to return to the countryside.
就是回不回农村
Including whether to take the postgraduate entrance exam.
包括考研会不会考研
I think taking the postgraduate exam involves too many sacrifices.
我觉得考研本身牺牲的太多
Taking the postgraduate exam is incredibly time-consuming.
考研这个东西是其实是非常的耗费精力
You spend so much time preparing for it.
你花那个时间去考
And there's no guarantee you'll pass.
哎呀不一定考得上
Then you have to spend more time studying if you do get in.
然后要花那个时间去读
So, what did you end up getting?
最终你得到了得到的是什么呢
And Zhang Jingchu took the AFI graduate program exam.
而且张静初考那个AFI那个研
Right?
对不对
So I highly recommend everyone visit my alma mater
所以我非常建议大家到我的母校
Kwantlen Polytechnic University, to pursue a two-year master’s degree and then come back.
那昆特兰理工大学啊去读研究生两年就能回来
This is the most critical point.
这是最关键的
It's about spending the least amount of money to achieve the most.
就是你要花最少的钱办最多的事啊
I truly believe that a master’s degree is a dream for many people. It's a dream. Perfectionism Everyone has it I want it too But let's be honest A master’s degree isn’t as crucial as people think
我真觉得研究生学历对于很多人来讲 是一个啊这个梦想啊 完美主义啊 别人都有 我也要有的一个东西 但是咱说实在的 这个研究生学历真的是没有那么的重要
And we’re in an era where qualifications aren’t everything
而且现在是一个轻学历的一个时代啊
I believe getting a higher education and reading college-level books is really important
我觉得受高等教育读大学阶段的书非常有必要
Especially for someone like me who’s a knowledge influencer
特别你像我做知识博主的来讲的话
If you want to be a knowledge influencer
如果说你要做知识博主
I'm not saying you're young
不是说你是一个年轻人
You're a fresh graduate
你应届毕业生
You just took the postgraduate entrance exam
你考研考也就考了
I really don't recommend that someone my age, a web celebrity
我真不建议说像我这个岁数的网红啊
goes back to retake the exam now
现在倒回去重新去考
this is called reverse studying
这叫倒读这个东西来讲
you've already entered the workforce
你现在这个人已经进入社会了
so don't go back to thinking about it
就不要再倒回去想啊
spending another two years as a student
再过两年学生生活
Otherwise, you might end up not getting either one.
否则你呃两个东西都不会去占着的啊
You can go for further studies.
你可以去进修
You can read and learn in your spare time.
你可以业余时间去读一读东西
But you must prioritize your career.
但是一定要以事业为中心
Because the time for school has passed.
因为学校那个阶段已经过去了之后
You must focus on your career.
一定要以事业为中心啊
Focus on your career.
事业为中心
There are many things you can do in your career.
事业上有很多事情可做
If you don't know how to proceed, you can
如果你不知道该怎么做来讲
That means you don't have the potential for a successful career.
那就说明你没有这个发展事业的可能性啊
Academics and career. And then comes the career. This is a normal sequence. So, even though my friend recommended me Talking about postgraduate studies, Encouraging everyone to pursue a master's degree, I still don't encourage people to do so.
学业职业 然后是事业 这是一个正常的一个顺序 所以呢虽然我的朋友推荐我啊 说一遍考研的事啊 鼓励大家考研 但是我仍然是不鼓励大家考研的
Because I think the return on investment is simply too low.
因为我认为投入产出比简直太小了啊
I suggest keeping the rural homestead rights.
然后我是建议大家保留农村的宅基地的
Regarding policy matters,
政策上的东西
Let's not overcomment
咱们不过度评论
But from a personal perspective,
但是我从个人来讲
If I had the chance,
如果我能有的话啊
I have a dream of a large country house.
因为我有一个乡间大豪宅的一个美梦啊
Of course, I also recommend finding a good designer,
当然来讲我也是建议大家找合适的设计师啊
There are many houses on Bilibili that are beautifully designed.
这个B站有很多特别做的特别好的大房子
You can actually commission such talented individuals to build your house.
其实大家可以委托这样的
If you have to spend money, so be it.
有才能的人帮你去盖房子
And buying a villa in the city,
花点钱就花点钱啊
To be honest, buying is one thing,
然后在城里边买别墅
But the renovation costs can be several million.
说实在的买是一回事
Not everyone is suited to own a villa.
装修又是好几百万
If you really want a villa,
那别墅这个东西来讲的不是人人都适合拥有
I suggest renting one instead.
我建议如果你真想要别墅的话
Renting a villa is relatively cheaper.
你不如去租别墅
Even in Beijing or Shanghai,
租别墅还是比较便宜的啊
There are options for 10,000 to 20,000 yuan per month.
就算是北京上海的话
You can rent a villa.
也有1万多2万的
If you don't have a large family,
这别墅可以租啊
There's no real need for a villa.
其实不是一个大家族的话
Especially for someone like me who lives alone,
其实没有必要弄别墅
I find it uncomfortable even in a three-room house.
特别是你像我就一个人的话
So, let's go back to what we discussed at the beginning with Zheng Qiang,
我连三间大瓦房住的都难受啊
And finally, the topic of rural homestead rights. Everyone has their own opinion. AI can certainly provide some insights and inspiration, But honestly, If I just followed AI's direction entirely,
所以这个东西咱们还是从最开始说到郑强 说到最后宅基地啊这个东西啊 一个人有一个人的看法啊 AI固然能给我一些感觉 有一些灵感上的提供
What would be the point of watching my show?
但是说实在的
This is today's morning chat, episode 507.
如果完全按AI的方向去解读的话
Then what's the point of watching my show?
那大家看我的节目还有什么意思呢